<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Joseph Levine</title>
    <description>A Jekyll theme for content-rich sites</description>
    <link>jablevine.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="jablevine.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2023 13:23:15 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2023 13:23:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v4.2.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hospital pricing, ambulances, and qualitative research</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;test&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;test&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;test&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>jablevine.com/articles/23/a-test-draft</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">jablevine.com/articles/23/a-test-draft</guid>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hospital pricing, ambulances, and qualitative research</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;My cohort-mate Elodie Chervin, a tall Frenchwoman with a better American accent than mine, presented in December a &lt;a href=&quot;https://jablevine.com/papers/Cooper%20et%20al_2022_Do%20Higher-Priced%20Hospitals%20Deliver%20Higher-Quality%20Care.pdf&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; she had worked on as a research assistant for Zach Cooper at Yale.&lt;label for=&quot;notemexl&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;notemexl&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;The notebook with my notes from Elodie’s talk mysteriously disappeared in Mexico (not mysterious, it was stolen from a rental car after the back window was smashed in). And I’m not going to actually read the paper; grad students don’t have time for that. So this is mostly based on memory. &lt;/span&gt; The paper is called “Do Higher-Priced Hospitals Deliver Higher-Quality Care?,” and finds positive results, with a caveat for market concentration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While higher-priced hospital services are better in areas with competitive markets, once the authors look at consolidated markets, the effect goes away.&lt;label for=&quot;deffgorev&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;deffgorev&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Or reverses? Don’t remember. &lt;/span&gt; There’s been a trend towards hospital mergers, larger “health systems,” and this is the bad guy. The path goes something like: mergers —&amp;gt; ↑ market consolidation —&amp;gt; ↓ competition —&amp;gt; ↑ prices, with no endogenous change in the level of care. So having higher prices makes you a better hospital (lol causality) in competitive markets, but there’s no reason for this to be true in consolidated markets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a graph which shows up often around people with an intellectual interest in inflation, like first-year microeconomics students or New York Times readers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/img/price-changes-in-usa-in-past-20-years-2294.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;figcaption class=&quot;maincolumn-figure&quot;&gt;Elodie used a different version which separated emergency hospital services from non-emergency hospital services.&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The moral is presumably that, while it’s great televisions are getting cheaper, the “important” stuff is getting more expensive faster than wages, and the only goods which are getting cheaper are boring, opiate of the masses consumer goods.&lt;label for=&quot;moore-id&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;moore-id&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Another plausible story is about the Moore’s law as a black hole for innovation. We’ve gotten unspeakably good at cramming transistors onto a chip, but this innovation hasn’t (yet) spilled over to revolutions in the healthcare sector. I like this story more, but it’s not asrelevant. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An aside — one of my soapboxes is the increasing fraction of for-profit nursing homes. Something like three-quarters of skilled nursing facilities (SNFs&lt;label for=&quot;snfsac-id&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;snfsac-id&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;There are many jokes about ‘sniffs’ among EMTs, with numerous possibilities of what the ‘S’ could stand for. &lt;/span&gt;) are for-profit, compared to one-third of hospitals. One example which has made my life sadder and smellier is HCR Manorcare, a chain of SNFs which Carlyle acquired in a messy LBO 20 years ago. I don’t have any evidence that PE-run SNFs are worse than privately owned facilities… oh wait, &lt;a href=&quot;https://jablevine.com/papers/Gupta%20et%20al_Does%20Private%20Equity%20Investment%20in%20Healthcare%20Benefit%20Patients.pdf&quot;&gt;yes I do&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;PE ownership increases short-term mortality by 13% and reduces other measures of patient well-being, while also increasing revenue per patient by 10%. Clinical and operational changes help to explain these effects, including declines in nursing staff and lower compliance with care standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a great paper — there’s a cool instrumental variables approach to deal with changing patient composition. And it brims with righteous anger: the authors aren’t afraid to write that their results imply “20,150 lives lost due to PE ownership over our twelve-year sample period.” Now, I’m slightly equivocating between PE-run and privately owned SNFs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back to Elodie’s work: identifying the effect of a hospital’s care is really tough econometric work, so they used&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a &lt;em&gt;fantastic&lt;/em&gt; identification strategy.&lt;label for=&quot;sidenote-id&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sidenote-id&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;It’s not original to this paper — Doyle et al. (2015) first used this IV strategy, and it’s becoming more widespread. &lt;/span&gt; Ambulance services, especially private ambulance companies, are messy and chaotic in just the right amount to give patients a plausibly exogenous hospital assignment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the end of the talk, I had a dozen questions written down for Elodie about ambulance data and the assumptions the research team made — how to deal with consolidation of ambulance companies? When ambulance crews bid for calls,&lt;label for=&quot;sidenote-id&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sidenote-id&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;This is a random sidenote &lt;/span&gt; are those patients treated as less randomly assigned?  Do they control for the quality of the snacks in the emergency room?&lt;label for=&quot;sidenote-id&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sidenote-id&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;This is a random sidenote &lt;/span&gt;  Did the team have data on patient hospital preference?&lt;label for=&quot;sidenote-id&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sidenote-id&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;This is a random sidenote &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t get to ask all of these questions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;label for=&quot;sidenote-id&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;sidenote-id&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Another member of my cohort, Daniel Barbosa, has been presenting a paper on police body cameras in Brazil with a remarkably similar identification strategy. If one of the other six of us can put together a paper on firefighters, we’ll have the trifecta. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interesting lives and ride alongs&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The UK is having it’s own ambulance based crisis at the moment&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 11:37:17 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>jablevine.com/articles/23/ambulances-and-research</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">jablevine.com/articles/23/ambulances-and-research</guid>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Restaurant: District Chophouse, Dulles Airport</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;District Chophouse, the only restaurant outside of security at Dulles International Airport, is a weird place. In my two hours at the centre-most table, I saw:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;•a flight attendant in her first week on the job, trying desperately for ten minutes to order a chicken ceasar salad, only to end up with &lt;em&gt;three&lt;/em&gt; chicken ceasar salads;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;•three of the palest ex-Marine’s i’ve ever seen, discussing Azerbaijan’s export policies in Virginia drawls;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;•the largest 2pm pours of Merlot I’ve seen since freshman year; seriously, some of these people were wearing white to fly and it was dangerous;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;•presumably at least a few spies of differing nationalities — if you want to meet with an agent before they flee the country, without subjecting yourself to the rigours of our TSA, this is an ideal spot.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what brought me here, drinking a $13 Blue Moon? A three hour layover, and the prospect of not seeing my mom until she flies over to Oxford once the weather turns pleasant. I walked through customs, she hopped on the Dulles Toll Road, and we had a furtive dead drop of our own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of state secrets, my mom was passing along a new driver’s license — mine had mysteriously disappeared&lt;label for=&quot;readlos&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;readlos&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Not mysterious. I lost it. &lt;/span&gt; in CDMX, just moments before attempting to rent a car to go climb a volcano.&lt;label for=&quot;grarr&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;grarr&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Thanks, Robi, for adding me as an additional driver and saving the day. &lt;/span&gt; The replacement had arrived at my parents’ house and&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The food was adequate and overpriced. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flydulles.com/store/district-chophouse&quot;&gt;menu&lt;/a&gt; has an impressive breakfast spread, and exactly five non-breakfast options, three of which are burgers.&lt;label for=&quot;menu&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;menu&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Filled out by a filet mignon and ‘fresh salmon with orange beurre blanc.’ &lt;/span&gt; My medium-rare burger was returned a robust medium-well; my mom’s medium-well steak was served with more than a hint of blood. Sweet potato fries and the pickle were far above average. They were not busy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All airport restaurants provoke an uncanny valley reaction — everything is &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; right, you could &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; be seated at a Sbarro in a mall in Poughkeepsie, but there’s a Truman Show feeling preventing normality. District Chophouse takes this a bit further, being outside the realm of the TSA. There’s a “patio” area outside the “door”,&lt;label for=&quot;door&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle sidenote-number&quot;&gt;&lt;/label&gt;&lt;input type=&quot;checkbox&quot; id=&quot;door&quot; class=&quot;margin-toggle&quot; /&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;sidenote&quot;&gt;Entirely the same as the area inside the door, but with a slightly higher ceiling. &lt;/span&gt; and “windows” facing the Alaska Airlines check-in counter. Twenty meters away, you can see taxis and ubers and spouses attempting to drop off customers and loved ones, and the Metropolitan Washington Airports Authority Police completely failing to keep traffic moving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Would I go back? I hope not. Minimizing time in airports is a high priority of my travel planning. Getting through security and achieving access to the cornucopia of Dunkin’ and Potbelly and The Kitchen by Wolfgang Puck should be any traveler’s goal. If you ever arrive at Dulles too early to check in, that’s your fault, and District Chophouse is an appropriate dessert.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2023 17:04:01 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>jablevine.com/articles/23/district-chophouse</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">jablevine.com/articles/23/district-chophouse</guid>
        
        
        <category>post</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
